Guide to the
Brown University Library
- Correspondence, Series VII
  - Chace, George Ide, 1808-1885 (1830), 1860 June 08
    To Executive Board .... VII. Expresses "views in regard to the aims, organization and conduct of the Department of Chemistry.".
  - Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916 (1849), 1860 July 26
    To the Executive Board .... VII. Resignation as professor of modern languages.
  - Vernon, Thomas, 1860 September 03
    To John Kingsbury .... VII. Resigns as trustee.
  - Kingsbury, John, 1801-1874 (1826), 1860 September 04
    To the Corporation .... VII. Signed also by Samuel G. Arnold, William Gammell, John R. Bartlett, and William Patten. On presentation of portrait of Nathan B. Crocker.
  - Gammell, William, 1812-1889 (1831), 1860 October 06
    Report of the com[mittee] on trien[nial] catalogue .... VII.
  - Kingsbury, John, 1801-1874 (1826), 1861 June 06
    To M. B. I. Goddard .... VII. Vote on salary of E. H. Cutler.
  - Kingsbury, John, 1801-1874 (1826), 1861 June 08
    To M. B. I. Goddard .... VII. Amount due President Sears is the same as paid quarterly to the German teacher.
  - Bishop, Nathan, 1808-1880 (1837), 1861 August 22
    To the Corporation .... VII. Resigning from Board of Fellows.
  - Patten, William Samuel, 1800-1873 (1818), 1861 September 02
    To the Corporation .... VII. Report of committee appointed to express the obligations of the Corporation to John Carter Brown for his gift of the Brown Lot. Appended letter from Committee to John Carter Brown, September 8, 1860.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1862 September 01
    Report of special committee on income & expenditure .... VII. Written and signed by Alva Woods, chairman. Signed also by Wm. S. Patten and Wm. Goddard. Notes special expenditures for repair of Manning Hall and salary of financial agent, Horace T. Love.
  - Turner, Thomas Goodwin, 1862 September 05
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1863
    [Reports of committee to ascertain in what way the income of the University may be increased and its annual expenses diminished] .... VII. Two reports.
  - Brown University, 1863 February 03
    [Subscription list for procuring a full-length portrait of Major General Ambrose E. Burnside] .... VII.
  - Shepard, Thomas Perkins, 1817-1877 (1836), 1863 May 03
    [Report of committee to procure the construction of paths east of the college buildings] .... VII.
  - Kingsbury, John, 1801-1874 (1826), 1863 December 12
    To R. H. Ives .... VII. Mr. Lyon is required to pay, in quarterly installments, for the current year a rent of $100 for the use of the Grammar School Building.
  - Gammell, William, 1812-1889 (1831), 1864 January 08
    To the Executive Board .... VII. Resignation as professor of history and political economy. Draft of letter with this.
  - Brown University--Executive Board, 1864 March 11
    [Resolution on resignation of William Gammell] .... VII.
  - Gammell, William, 1812-1889 (1831), 1864 March 15
    To John Kingsbury .... VII. Thanking him for resolution of Executive Board on his resignation.
  - Hill, Nathaniel Peter, 1832-1900 (1856), 1864 April 23 - 1865 January 01
    To the Executive Board] .... VII. Requesting a leave of absence from April 23, 1864 to January 1, 1865 to accept a temporary job to supplement his income.
  - Kingsbury, John, 1801-1874 (1826), 1864 April 13
    [Report on salary due Professor Hill for services during absence of Professor Chace] .... VII.
  - Kingsbury, John, 1801-1874 (1826), 1864 June 16
    To L. Taylor .... VII. States salaries of Professors Pierce and Angell and payment due.
  - Brown University--Corporation--Executive board, 1865 April 14
    [Extract from records] .... VII. Authorizing treasurer to collect interest on stock and loans of the United Sates belonging to Brown University. Extracts, dated January 21 and March 29, 1867, certified by John Kingsbury.
  - Borden, Jefferson, 1865 September 12
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1866 September 06
    [Extracts from minutes] .... VII. Notes particularly the resignation of Robert H. Ives as treasurer.
  - Sprague, William, 1831-1915 (h1861), 1866 September 09
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1867
    [Resolutions on the death of Robinson Potter Dunn] .... VII.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1867
    [Resolutions on the death of Samuel Boyd Tobey] .... VII.
  - Chace, George Ide, 1808-1885 (1830), 1867 April 04
    To John Kingsbury .... VII. Report of gift of chemical apparatus by John Carter Brown and Robert H. Ives.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1867 April 17
    [Resolutions accepting resignation of Barnas Sears] .... VII. On verso, Resolutions...by William S. Patten. Rough draft of resolutions with this.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1867 April 17
    [Report of committee to receive funds from retiring treasurer, Robert H. Ives] .... VII. Written and signed by A. Woods for the committee. Appended are copies of committee's certificate of receipt and receipt by new treasurer, Marshall Woods, November 21, 1866.
  - Anderson, Martin Brewer, 1815-1890, 1867 June 07
    To Rev. [Baron] Stow .... VII. Declining presidency of Brown University.
  - Stow, Baron, 1801-1869, 1867 June 17
    To John Kingsbury .... VII. Informs him that committee of six have informed Dr. M. B. Anderson of his election as President of Brown University.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1867 July 02
    [Report of Committee on the Department of Analytical Chemistry] .... VII. Report by Thos. P. Shepard for the Committee.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1867 July 12
    [Report of Committee on physical sciences] .... VII. Signed by G. L. Collins, chairman.
  - Pierce, Edward Lillie, 1829-1897 (1850), 1867 August 09
    To Wm. Gammell .... VII. Lists reasons why honorary LL.D. degree should be conferred upon Dr. Samuel Gridley Howe.
  - Brown University--Corporation--Committee on presidential nominations, 1867-1868
    [Minutes of meetings and report to Corporation] .... VII. Twelve items written between July 10, 1867 and February 6, 1868. Appointment of George Ide Chace as President pro tempore. Nomination of Ezekiel Gilman Robinson; upon his refusal, nomination of Alexis Caswell.
  - Gammell, William, 1812-1889 (1831), 1867 August 24
    To A[lva] Woods .... VII. Recommending Samuel Gridley Howe for honorary degree.
  - Chace, George Ide, 1808-1885 (1830), 1867 September 04
    To John Kingsbury .... VII. Suggests Brown University comply as soon as possible with conditions of an Act of Congress concerning the donation of lands.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1867 September 05
    Report of the committee for examination in the department of rhetorican and English literature .... VII. Submitted by S. L. Caldwell, R. B. Duane, and J. G. Vose. Mentions death of Professor Dunn.
  - Brown University, 1867 October 01
    Subscriptions for the Portrait Gallery in Rhode Island Hall .... VII. In hand of Reuben A. Guild.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1868
    [Report of committee on the department of the Latin language] .... VII. Written and signed by John Kingsbury for the committee. "Prof. Lincoln has assumed the whole of the Instruction in this Department.".
  - Bowen, Henry Clark, 1785-1867 (1802), 1868 July 10
    To [John] Kingsbury .... VII. Suggests honorary degree for Samuel S. Scammell, who attended Brown, but never received degree.
  - Warren, Jonah Goulding, 1812-1884 (1835), 1868 July 10
    To [Samuel L.] Caldwell .... VII. Cannot meet with the committee on Saturday.
  - Chase, Stephen Abbott, 1869 August
    To the chancellor of Brown University .... VII. Resigns as trustee.
  - McKenzie, William Scott, 1832-1896, 1869 August 09
    To S. L. Caldwell .... VII. Recommending that Silas Alward be awarded A.M. degree ad eundem. Biographical information about Alward.
  - Chase, Stephen Abbott, 1869 August 20
    To.... VII. Asks him to render his resignation as trustee as he does not know the name of the chancellor.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1869 September 02
    [Resolutions of the death of James H. Duncan] .... VII. Resolutions offered by Alva Woods.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1868 September 02
    [Report of committee on president's report] .... VII. Written and signed by A. Caswell, chairman. Comments on distribution of scholarships, need for increased accommodation for the library.
  - Whittier, John Greenleaf, 1807-1892, 1869 September 10
    To Alva Woods .... VII. Negative photostat. Concerning his election to the Corporation; questions his ability to meet expectations.
  - Hazard, Rowland Gibson, 1801-1888, 1869 September 11
    To S. S. Bradford .... VII. Accepting election as trustee.
  - Duncan, Rebecca W., 1869 September 20
    To S. S. Bradford .... VII. Thanking the Corporation for resolutions on death of her father, James Henry Duncan.
  - Pollard, Andrew, 1814-1886, 1870 June 24
    To the Board of Fellows .... VII. Signed also by George D. Miles. Recommending William Watson Waterman for honorary A.M. degree.
  - Wayland, Heman Lincoln, 1830-1898 (1849), 1870 June 24
    To John Kingsbury .... VII. Will of the late President Wayland provides that his executors may make changes in disposition of President's premiums within five years after his decease. Writer asks for extension of three years.
  - Kingsbury, John, 1801-1874 (1826), 1870 July 30
    To Dr. Caswell and W. S. Patten .... VII. Cannot accept appointment to committee "to whom was referred that part of the President's Report which relates to the erection of a new building for a Museum of Natural History.".
  - Potter, William H., 1870 November 26
    To J. C. Stockbridge .... VII. Recommends Prof. Buckland and D. A. Daboll for honorary degrees.
  - Huntington, F. D., 1871 April 10
    To .... VII. Recommends Rev. George H. McKnight for honorary D. D. degree.
  - Park, Edwards Amasa, 1808-1900 (1826), 1871 June 17
    To John Kingsbury .... VII. Recommends Henry Allon and Warren Lovering for honorary degrees.
  - Chace, George Ide, 1808-1885 (1830), 1871 June 26
    To the Corporation .... VII. Tenders his resignation as professor of intellectual and moral philosophy.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1871 June 28
    [Report of the committee on cooperation of the alumni] .... VII. Written and signed by Alexis Caswell. Further suggests organization of the University Grammar School under faculty of Brown University.
  - Brown University--Real estate committee, 1871 June 29
    [Report recommending exchange of land] .... VII. Recommends exchange of land with H. G. Russell to obtain for Brown University the land between the college campus and Thayer Street belonging to the heirs of Moses B. Ives. Signed, Alva Woods and Moses B. Ives. With this, document by H. G. Russell, April 22, 1871, agreeing to exchange, and document by Robert H. Ives, July 2, 1871, receipt for quit claim deed from Brown University to Ann A. Ives and H. G. Russell.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1872
    [Notes on Dr. Park's absence from Corporation meetings for five years] .... VII.
  - Pirkey, Oval, 1872 January 18
    To Charles E. Aaron .... VII. Would welcome a degree from Brown University.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1872 January 24
    [Vote of appreciation to George Ide Chace] .... VII. Requests that his service be continued.
  - Chace, George Ide, 1808-1885 (1830), 1872 January 27
    To A[lvah] Hovey .... VII. Cannot comply with first resolution passed by the Corporation the second resolution does not require an immediate answer.
  - Appleton, John Howard, 1844-1930 (1863), 1872 May
    To the Executive and Advisory Committee of the Corporation .... VII. Requests permission to finish instruction for term two weeks earlier in order to go to Europe. "Request granted A. Caswell.".
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1874-1875
    [Reports of the Committee to superintend the construction of the addition to Rhodes Island Hall] .... VII. Written and signed by A. Caswell for the committee.
  - Chace, George Ide, 1872 February 05
    To Committee .... VII.
  - Guild, Reuben Aldridge, 1822-1899 (1847), 1875 June 17
    To the Corporation .... VII. Reports in behalf of the Alumni Association the nominations for vacancies on the Board of Trustees.
  - Hamlin, Charles E., 1877 July 06
    To Marshall Woods .... VII. Accepts professorship in Brown University.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1878 June 01
    To A. A. Reed] .... VII. Acknowledgment of gift to museum of birds and animals. Signed, E. G. Robinson and J. W. P. Jenks.
  - Davis, Isaac, 1799-1883 (1822), 1879 May 26
    To the Corporation .... VII. Resignation from Board of Fellows.
  - Parker, Gilman Parker, 1856-1902 (1878), 1880
    To the Advisory and Executive Committee .... VII. Suggests plan for the renting of rooms.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1880 June 17
    Report of the committee on the English language and literature .... VII. Signed by R. Hazard, William Gammell, A. N. Arnold, A. B. Chace.
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee, 1880 June 25
    [Resolution giving permission to Dr. E. T. Caswell to exhibit portrait of Alexis Caswell in store of Tilden and Thurber] .... VII. Seven signatures added.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1881
    [Report of committee on new plan for defraying expense of the commencement dinner] .... VII. Signed by Heman Lincoln, J. C. Stockbridge, A. B. Chace.
  - Brown University--Committee on reconstruction of University Hall, 1881
    [Reports] .... VII. Two reports submitted by C. S. Bradley.
  - Duncan, Alexander, 1805-1889, 1881 May 30
    To [William] Gammell .... VII.76. Will comply with request of Brown University for his portrait.
  - Brown University--Associated Alumni, 1881 June 11
    To the Corporation of Brown University .... VII. Presenting portraits of Rowland Gibson Hazard, Theron Metcalf, John Brown Francis, John Henry Clifford, portrait bust of Lafayette Sabine Foster.
  - Woods, Anne Brown Francis, 1881 June 13
    To [William] Gammell .... VII. Concerning portrait of her father, Governor Francis, which she presents to Brown University.
  - Whittier, John Greenleaf, 1807-1892, 1881 August 10
    To Richard Atwater .... VII. Expresses the hope that Brown University will open its doors to women students.
  - Brown University--Christian Association, 1882
    To the Corporation .... VII. Request of Christian Association and Missionary Society of Inquiry for a room in the university for their use. Signed by James A. Brown, Isaac B. Burgess, George B. Wakeman.
  - Woods, Marshall, 1824-1899 (1845), 1882 June 22
    To the Corporation .... VII. Resignation as treasurer of Brown University.
  - Young Men's Christian Association, Providence, R.I., 1882 September 29
    [Agreement with Brown University for use of gymnasium by students] .... VII. Signed by William D. Nisbet.
  - Brown University--Corporation
    [Resolution accepting portraits] .... VII. n.d. Portraits of Horatio N. Slater, Isaac Davis, Alexander Duncan and Romeo Elton, given by the Associated Alumni.
  - Brown University--Christian Association, 1882
    To the Corporation .... VII. Request of Christian Association and Missionary Society of Inquiry for a room in the university for their use. Signed by James A. Brown, Isaac B. Burgess, Geo. B. Wakeman.
  - Brown University--Real estate committee, 1883 June 21
    [Report on attempt to purchase lot adjoining east campus] .... VII. Signed by five members of committee. Owner of lot refused to sell.
  - Brown University--Real estate committee, 1883
    [Report on fencing the ball grounds] .... VII. Signed by five members of the committee.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1883 June 21
    Report of committee on readjustment of the duties pertaining to the office of the registrar .... VII. Written and signed by William Gammell. Also signed by Merrick Lyon, Wm. Goddard, Rowland Hazard, Daniel Leach. On need for greater supervision of the University's property. Duties of steward and registrar may be performed by one person.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1883 September
    [Report of committee on heating Manning Hall] .... VII. Signed by A. Woods, Marshall Woods, Merrick Lyon, Daniel Leach. With this, copies of bids for work by Ellery Millard and Le Bosquet Bros.
  - Upton, Winslow, 1853-1914 (1875), 1884 May 08
    [Statement in regard to proposed laboratory] .... VII.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1884 June 10
    [Report of committee on observatory] .... VII.75. Signed by William Gammell and E. G. Robinson.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1884 September 03
    [Report of committee on the duties of the registrar] .... VII. Written and signed by William Gammell. Signed also by Wm. Goddard, Merrick Lyon, Daniel Leach, Rowland Hazard, Arnold B. Chace, E. G. Robinson. Recommending division of registrar's present duties between registrar and steward. Suggests engaging Gilman P. Robinson as Registrar and Archibald G. Delaney as Steward.
  - Brown University--Faculty, 1887 May 03
    To the Board of Fellows .... VII. Submitted by Nathaniel F. Davis, Secretary of the Faculty. Requests the new rules be observed in conferring the degree of Master of Arts. Note added by Alvah Hovey, July 25, 1887, stating that he will recommend that the Board grant the request.
  - Lincoln, John Larkin, 1817-1891 (1836), 1887 June 15
    To the Corporation .... VII. Requesting leave of absence to go abroad for his wife's health and continuance of his salary on condition that he provide for instruction of his classes at his own expense.
  - Wilcox, C. F., 1887 July 18
    To S. L. Caldwell .... VII. Mrs. Burrough concerned by Corporation's failure to acknowledge her gift of a portrait of David Howell.
  - Porter, Henry Kirke, 1840-1921 (1860), 1888 February 21
    To the Corporation .... VII. On the purchase of a collection of casts made for the University; praises John Larkin Lincoln as a teacher.
  - Brown University--Class of 1868, 1888 June 20
    To the President and the Corporation .... VII. Written by William Carey Poland. On the class fund, which is to be used to purchase plaster casts and other material for the illustration of classical art. The fund is to be turned over to the treasurer and a committee appointed. Mentions purchase of cast of Hermes of Praxitiles.
  - Lincoln, John Larkin, 1817-1891 (1836), 1888 August 20
    To the Corporation .... VII. Announcing gift of $250 from George Van Ness Lothrop for purchase of books on classical subjects for the library.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1888 August 23
    [Report of committee on finance] .... VII. Signed by William Goddard, Mortimer H. Hartwell, Daniel Leach. Report on resolutions of the Corporation concerning funds of the University.
  - Woods, Marshall, 1824-1899 (1845), 1888 September 04
    To [Samuel L.] Caldwell .... VII. Does not wish to be nominated for reelection to the investment committee.
  - Granger, Abraham Holley, 1888 September 12
    To [Samuel L.] Caldwell .... VII. Feels that the records "ought to show by whose authority the existing laws of college were ordained.".
  - Park, Edwards Amasa, 1808-1900 (1826), 1888 December 13
    To [John C.] Stockbridge .... VII. Concerning Asa Messer.
  - Phelps, Sylvanus Dryden, 1816-1895 (1844), 1889 June 13
    To S. L. Caldwell .... VII. Inquires about an A.M. degree for his son, Arthur Stevens Phelps.
  - Burrage, Henry Sweetser, 1837-1926 (1861), 1889 June 28
    To [Samuel L.] Caldwell .... VII. Accepts appointment as a trustee.
  - Green, Arnold, 1838-1903 (1858), 1889 July 04
    To S. L. Caldwell .... VII. Accepts appointment as trustee.
  - Duncan, Samuel White, 1838-1898 (1860), 1889 September 18
    To S. L. Caldwell .... VII. 1889(09-18) Accepts appointment as a fellow.
  - Blackinton, Mary D., 1892 February 12
    To the Corporation .... VII. Presenting $1000 for the James Fletcher Blackinton scholarship for indigent students in memory of her husband.
  - Foster, William Eaton, 1893 August 08
    To [Thomas D.] Anderson .... VII. With enclosures: an extract from Dr. Woolsey's article, an extract from Foster's article in The Nation, also a circular letter seeking the discontinuance of awarding honorary Ph.D. degrees.
  - Jenks, John Whipple Potter, 1819-1894 (1838), 1893 September 04
    To the Corporation .... VII. Reports alterations to museum: need for permanent fund for museum; purchase of mounted lioness.
  - Hazard, Rowland Gibson, 1855-1918 (1876), 1894 June 22
    To Thomas D. Anderson .... VII. Accepting election as trustee.
  - Olney, Richard, 1835-1916 (1856), 1894 June 23
    To Thomas D. Anderson .... VII. Written by a private secretary. Acknowledging election as fellow.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1894 September 17
    [Resolution on the death of Ezekiel Gilman Robinson] .... VII. Rough draft.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1895 August 13
    [Agreement with Wm. A. Chapman & Co.] .... VII. For addition to boiler house at Brown. Signed by A. B. Chace.
  - Hill, John E., 1895 December 07
    Reports on the future development of the present campus of Brown University .... VII. Signed by John E. Hill and Norman M. Isham. With map of property of Brown University showing proposed buildings.
  - Adams, Robert John, 1896 May 18
    To [Thomas D.] Anderson .... VII. Recommending Rev. George E. Horr for honorary D.D. degree.
  - Park, Edwards Amasa
    To Board of Trustees .... VII. Resigns as fellow because of ill health.
  - Rhode Island Pharmaceutical Association, 1897
    To the Advisory and Executive Committee .... VII. Requesting that a course in pharmacy be established at Brown. Signed by ten members of the association. With a tentative outline of the proposed course and a letter by Hermon Carey Bumpus, June 4, 1897, commenting on the proposal; and printed report of committee to consider establishing a school of pharmacy.
  - Lawrence, William, 1897 April 10
    To Henry S. Burrga .... VII. Glad to hear that Sumner U. Shearman has received D.D. degree.
  - Burrage, Henry Sweetser, 1837-1926 (1861), 1897 April 12
    To B. F. Clarke .... VII. Recommending Rev. Sumner U. Shearman for honorary D.D. degree.
  - Stiness, John H., 1897 June 21
    To Thomas D. Anderson .... VII. Accepts election as a fellow.
  - Poland, William Carey, 1846-1929 (1868), 1899 June 19
    To the President and Corporation .... VII. Recommends the placement of the busts of Washington and Franklin in the Museum of Fine Arts under his direction. MB1A.